<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famous and renowned history of the nine worthies of the world ... giving a true historical account of their glorious lives, victories, and deat[hs].</title>
            <author>R. B., 1632?-1725?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12126061</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12126061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54609</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54609)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 90:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famous and renowned history of the nine worthies of the world ... giving a true historical account of their glorious lives, victories, and deat[hs].</title>
                  <author>R. B., 1632?-1725?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.O. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Nathaniel Crouch [i.e. R.B.]. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Last part of imprint cut off. W.O. is probably William Onley, who printed 1697-1709. The first ed. of this work was in 1687.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Folger Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. Hector, Son of Priamus, King of Troy -- II. Alexander the Great ... -- III. Julius Caesar ... -- IV. Joshua, Captain-general of Israel -- V. David, King of Israel -- VI. Judas Maccabeus ... VII. Arthur, the famous British king -- VIII. Charles the Great, Emperour of Germany -- IX. Godfrey of Battoigne, King of Jerusalem.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54609:1"/>
            <p>The Famous and Renowned HISTORY OF THE Nine Worthies of the World; <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Hector</hi> Son of <hi>Priamus,</hi> King of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, who firſt Conquered the World.</item>
               <item>III. <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> the firſt Emperour of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Captain-General of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> a valiant Jewiſh Commander.</item>
               <item>VII. <hi>Arthur,</hi> the famous Britiſh King.</item>
               <item>VIII. <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, Emperour of <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IX. <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> King of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Giving a true Hiſtorical Account of their Glorious Lives, Victories and Deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>townscape of a harbour town below rolling hills</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. O.</hi> and are to be ſold by the Bookſellers of
<hi>Pye-corner</hi> and <hi>London by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54609:2"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of the Nine WORTHIES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The Noble Actions, Life, and Death of the Famous and Renowned <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> Prince of <hi>Troy,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>I Suppoſe there is few who have not heard of the famous Siege of <hi>Troy,</hi> once a renowned City in <hi>Aſia the Leſs,</hi> againſt which all the Power of <hi>Greece</hi> fought ten Years, e're they could ſubdue, and utterly deſtroy it: But being now to write of the glorious Actions of the <hi>Nine Worthies of the World,</hi> whoſe famous Valour has made Men ſtand amazed, and tranſmitted their Names and worthy Deeds to Poſterity; I muſt, however, ſay ſomething of that War, which has employed ſo many Pens, Antient and Modern, to ſet forth the Life and noble Atchivements of the Every-renowned and Valiant <hi>Hector,</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Priamus,</hi> King of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This famous City, commanding once ſo many Realms in <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſtood on the Coaſt of the Aegean-Sea, on the Aſian ſide, near the <hi>Heleſpont,</hi> called now the Streight of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> over-againſt the Cherſoneſus of <hi>Thrace,</hi> water'd by the famous Rivers <hi>Scamander</hi> and <hi>Simois;</hi> after changing his Name, till at length it was called <hi>Illium</hi> and <hi>Troy,</hi> and was twice ſubdued by <hi>Hercules;</hi> and
<hi>Priamus,</hi> Son to King <hi>Laomedon,</hi> and <hi>Heſione</hi> his Daughter, were carried Captives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Greece;</hi> the firſt of them was ranſom'd, but the latter being very beautiful, King <hi>Telamon,</hi> Father to <hi>Ajax,</hi> kept her for his Pleaſure, and would by no Entreaty conſent to reſtore her; though <hi>Priamus,</hi> after the Death of his Father
<hi>Laomedon,</hi> coming to the Crown, ſent <hi>Antenor,</hi> one of his chief Nobles, to
<hi>Telamon</hi>'s Court, to ſolicite her Delivery, by whom, and other Princes of the Greeks, he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed with Scorn, and terrible Threats. But <hi>Priamus</hi> concluding himſelf now ſtrong enough to be revenged on the Greeks, for the Injury and Affront done to him, in the detaining his Siſter, called his Sons and Nobles to Councel, laying the matter before them, and requiring Advice: All the Nobles approved of the Deſign; but <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> and
<hi>Helenus,</hi> two of his Sons, perſwaded him from it, as an Attempt full of Danger; as likewiſe did <hi>Caſſandra</hi> his Daughter, who was a Propheteſs, and ever ſpoke Truth, but never could have any Credit to be believed. However, the King being ſtedfaſtly bent on the matter, ordered his Son <hi>Paris,</hi> at whoſe Conception Queen <hi>Hecuba,</hi> his Mother, dreamed ſhe brought forth a Fire-brand that
<pb facs="tcp:54609:2"/> ſet all <hi>Troy</hi> in a Flame, was with his Brother <hi>Diophebus</hi> ſent to
<hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> with many Ships and armed Men, where King <hi>Manelaus</hi> reigned, and there being entertained as Gueſt, they in his Abſence ſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Queen, the fair
<hi>Hellena,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Ledea,</hi> with many of her Ladies; and laying the City waſt, brought with them great Riches to <hi>Troy;</hi> where <hi>Paris</hi> was married, as
<hi>Venus</hi> had promiſed him, to <hi>Hellena,</hi> the moſt beautiful Lady in the World.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Menelaus</hi> no ſooner heard of this great Injury done him, but he conſulted with King <hi>Agamemnon</hi> his Brother, and other Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> who looking upon it as an inſufferable Affront done to all the Eſtates, reſolved upon a War, vowing once more to level the Walls of <hi>Troy;</hi> appointing <hi>Agamemnon</hi> General over all the Forces. So with a thouſand Ships paſſed from <hi>Europe</hi> to <hi>Aſia,</hi> and took
<hi>Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi> after a ſtout Reſiſtance made by the Trojans, who gariſoned the ſtrong Caſtle; then coming near the City, they Landed, but not without great Effuſion of Blood on both ſides, ſo that the Sea became red; for <hi>Hector,</hi> who by his Father's Appointment, was General of the Trojans, advancing to Succour his Men that fainted, with a mighty two-handed Sword, levelled all in his way, killing King <hi>Proteſilaus,</hi> as he came with a huge force to ſtop his Fury; and ſoon after King <hi>Patarocleus,</hi> who came upon him with two thouſand Men, whoſe rich Armour he coveted to take, but was hindred by King <hi>Menon,</hi> with a great Power; which King, after the Slaughter of Multitudes of his Men, he ſlew in Revenge of that Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, driving many of the Greeks into the Sea: but at laſt, the ſtrong
<hi>Achilles, Menelaus, Agamennon, Ajax, Diomed, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes, Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus,</hi> and other valiant Princes and Captains, getting on Shore, ſo encouraged their Men, that the Fight continued exceeding bloody till Night parted them, and then the Trojans retired to the City.</p>
               <p>Early the next Morning the Trojans took the Field, and found the Greeks encamped not far from the City, when the Trumpets ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Battle, the two Armies joyned more furiouſly than before; and <hi>Hector</hi> fell on like an impetuous Storm, making whole Lanes of Dead before him, at every ſtroke giving Death, making Heads and Limbs to fly about the Plain, till he came where King <hi>Humerus</hi> fought ſucceſsfully, him he encountered, and ſoon overthrew with the ſlaughter of moſt of his Men, and preſſing forward, came where <hi>Achilles</hi> and his Mirmydons made great Deſtruction, overthrowing that ſtrong Champion, and ſlaying his Horſe, and had ſurely ſlain <hi>Achilles,</hi> had not his Men ruſhed violently to his Succour, and loſt many of their Lives to ſave him; and ſo preſſing on, he threw fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Brands on the Grecian Fleet, and ſet part of it on Fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
<pb facs="tcp:54609:3"/> this Day he had gained aſſured Victory, had he not met <hi>Ajax,</hi> in the fierce Encounter, and knowing him, ſpared his Life, and by him was perſwaded to a Seſſation of Arms for that time, and making a Truce, ſo that the Retreat was ſounded, much againſt the Will of the Conquering Trojans; which Over-ſight, coſt him his Life, and the Deſtruction of his Family, with the Ruin of the City.</p>
               <p>The Greeks having gained a Truce, recruited with freſh Forces, ſecured their Fleet with Trenches, and after this, and ſome other dreadful Battles, they plainly perceived, unleſs
<hi>Hector</hi> was ſlain, all their Hopes of winning <hi>Troy</hi> was in Vain, and that they ſhould rather periſh with their whole Army; they then held a Conſult how to bring it to paſs by any means; and in the Concluſion that Task was impoſed on <hi>Achilles,</hi> the Fierceſt and Strongeſt of all the Greeks; who watched many Opportunities, but was as often worſted and wounded in all the fair Encounters, and moſt of his Mirmydons, the valianteſt of the Soldiers ſlain; till one Day, contrary to the Intreaty of his Wife <hi>Andromache,</hi> who dreamed if he went that Day to the Field, he would be ſlain, as alſo the King, and the Tears of his Mother and Siſters, hearing <hi>Margetton,</hi> his natural Brother was ſlain, and the Trojans in Rout, he armed, and deſperately ruſhing on, ſlew a Multitude with his own Hand, and reſtored the Battle; but having taken a King in rich Armour Priſoner, as he caſt his Shield behind him, to lead him out of the Ranks, his Breaſt being Defenceleſs,
<hi>Achilles</hi> ſuddenly came upon him, incloſed him with his Men, and run his Spear into his Body, ſo that he fell down dead, and with him dyed all the Hopes of <hi>Troy;</hi> for though
<hi>Achilles</hi> was ſoon after ſlain by <hi>Paris, Phyrrus</hi> his Son, no leſs in Strength and Courage arriving in the Camp, <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Tragilus,</hi> King
<hi>Priamus</hi>'s Sons, being ſlain, and the <hi>Palladium,</hi> which was the Safe-gaurd of
<hi>Troy,</hi> ſtole by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> and <hi>Diomede,</hi> who ſlew the Warders of the Tower, who kept it; the City was ſoon after taken by the means of a mighty Wooden-Horſe the Greeks dedicated to <hi>Pallas,</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone, as they feigned, for the Theft of the
<hi>Palladium;</hi> which, upon the ſuppoſed Departure of the Enemy, was, by the Perſwaſion of one <hi>Sinon,</hi> a crafty Greek, drawn into the Gity, and the Walls broke down to give it entrance; when in the Night he let out the armed Men in the Belly of it, who ſeized the Gate, called in their Companions, ſlew the King, laid the City in Aſhes, and carried the Queen, her Daughters, and moſt that eſcaped the Sword, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:54609:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Life, Actions, and Death of <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> King of
<hi>Macedon,</hi> who conquered the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander</hi> from his many glorious Exploits and amazing Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Sir-named, <hi>The Great,</hi> was the Son of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> by <hi>Olympius</hi> his Queen; this <hi>Philip</hi> before his Death brought all <hi>Greece</hi> under his Subjection, and intended to war on the Perſian Monarchy, then flouriſhing in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and Part of
<hi>Africa,</hi> of vaſt Extent, governed by King <hi>Darius;</hi> but being ſlain before he put his Intendments in Execution, his Son <hi>Alexander</hi> aſſembled the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian States at
<hi>Corinth;</hi> and was by them choſen General of their Armies in his Father's ſtead; but ſoon after, by the Perſwaſion of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the Orator, corrupted with the Gold of <hi>Perſia,</hi> the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians, Athenians, and Thebans revolted from him, and made an Alliance with <hi>Darius;</hi> but <hi>Alexander</hi> ſoon reduced them to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, levelling the City of <hi>Thebes</hi> to the Ground, and ſelling the Citizens for Slaves.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſettled his Affairs in <hi>Greece,</hi> and put to Death all thoſe he ſuſpected could diſturd its Quiet in his Abſence, diſtributing his Treaſure amongſt his Commanders and Soldiers, reſerving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Hope of the World's Empire for himſelf, he paſſed into <hi>Aſia</hi> with an Army of 30000 Foot, and 4500 Horſe, moſtly of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers who had ſerved his Father; which ſmall Number <hi>Darius</hi> ſo much deſpiſed, that he ſent to his Lieutenant in the <hi>Leſſer Aſia,</hi> to fall upon and deſtroy them, but to take <hi>Alexander</hi> alive, to ſcourge him, and ſend him bound in Chains to
<hi>Babylon,</hi> where he reſided. But it fell out much otherwiſe than he expected, for with his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Men, he overthrew ſeveral Armies commanded by the Perſian Lieutenants, with almoſt incredible Slaughter, taking moſt of the ſtrong Places in the Way as he marched, which rouzed King <hi>Darius</hi> from his Eaſe and Luxury of his Court, to raiſe the whole Strength of his Kingdom, in hopes to drive out an Enemy now grown ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable to him, and a mighty Battle was fought between the Plains of <hi>Abraſtum,</hi> where he overthrew an Army 600000 Perſians, with the Loſs only of 9 Foot-men, and 100 Horſe-men, and taking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rich Plunder; having buried the Dead, and erected ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Monuments in Token of his Victory, upon which a great Part of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſubmitted to him.</p>
               <p>After this Battle, he marched to the City of <hi>Gordium,</hi> where in the Temple of
<hi>Jupiter,</hi> he cut the Gordian Knot in two, with his Sword, of which there went a Propheſie, That whoever could unfold it,
<pb facs="tcp:54609:4"/> ſhould be King of that Country; and having garriſoned that City, marched on, but fearing to be entangled in the narrow Paſſages of the huge Mountain <hi>Taurus,</hi> he marched ſpeedily over it, his Foot marching five hundred Furlongs without Reſpite, and ſo he came to
<hi>Turſus,</hi> where being taken with the pleaſant River <hi>Cydnus,</hi> he plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into it to cool and refreſh himſelf when hot, which cauſed an Ague-fit; and when <hi>Philip</hi> his Phyſician preſented him a Portion, he took it boldly, though he had a Letter ſent him, that
<hi>Philip</hi> was bribed by <hi>Darius</hi> to poiſon him; which Letter he delivered to
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> whilſt he was drinking the Potion, who read it undauntedly, and ſoon after
<hi>Alexander</hi> recovered.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Darius</hi> approached with a recruited Army of 300000 Foot, 100000 Horſe; when
<hi>Alexander</hi> encouraging his Soldiers, and extolling their Valour, who had broke through ſo many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and been ever victorious, he cauſed the Charge to be ſounded, and the two Armies ruſhed together with great Fury and Violence; but after a bloody Encounter, in which both Kings were wounded, the Perſians gave way, after 30000 Foot and 10000 Horſe were ſlain, and 4000 taken Priſoners, with the Loſs of no more than 130 Foot, and 150 Horſe of the Macedonians; and all <hi>Darius</hi>'s Treaſure of Gold, Silver, Jewels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fell into the Hands of the Victors; and among the Captive, were the Mother, Wife, and two Daughters of <hi>Darius,</hi> who fell on their Knees with piteous Cries before <hi>Alexander,</hi> expecting no leſs than Death, or worſe Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but he kindly raiſed and comforted them, cauſing them to be honouaably attended, and well-uſed; and falling into Love with the beauteous <hi>Barſione,</hi> one of the captive Ladies, he got a Son on her, whom he named <hi>Hercules:</hi> and after that married <hi>Statira,</hi> the eldeſt Daughter to <hi>Darius,</hi> giving <hi>Pariſatis</hi> to his dear Friend <hi>Haeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton;</hi> and ſeizing on the Perſian Fleet, marched unto
<hi>Syria,</hi> where many of the Eaſtern Kings who had been tributary to <hi>Darius,</hi> came and layed their Crowns at his Feet; moſt of them, receiving them again as his Bounty, to be tributary under him. Then he paſſed from <hi>Syria</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> taking all the Cities in his Way: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been reputed to be the Son of <hi>Jupiter Ammon,</hi> and not of King <hi>Philip,</hi> who had put away his Mother upon her confeſſing <hi>Jupiter</hi> came in the Shape of a Dragon, and got him in the Abſence of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> he enquired of that, and other Events at the the Temple of <hi>Ammon,</hi> where the flattering Prieſts declared him to be the Son of <hi>Jupiter Ammon;</hi> and that both Victories in all Wars, and the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all Lands were granted to him; charging his Followers to adore him as a God: which puffed him up with ſuch Pride, which,
<pb facs="tcp:54609:4"/> together with the Luxury of <hi>Aſia,</hi> utterly debauched his Virtues: for complaining of which, <hi>Parmenio,</hi> one of his greateſt Captains, was by his Command flead alive, and his Son <hi>Philotes</hi> ſlain.</p>
               <p>After this, he built a City on the Sea-coaſt of <hi>Egypt,</hi> calling it
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> from his own Name, and ſettled a Colony of Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians in it. And here
<hi>Darius</hi> writ to him to part his Empire with him, and that he ſhould freely enjoy his Part with his Daughter; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he offered him a vaſt Sum to redeem his Mother, Wife, and Daughters; but he refuſed all, unleſs he would ſurrender up the whole Empire of <hi>Perſia:</hi> Upon which <hi>Darius</hi> reſolving to try ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Field, raiſed an Army of 400000 Foot, and
100000 Horſe; but in his March heard his Wife was dead, and that <hi>Alexander</hi> had buried her very honourably, and wept at her Funeral, uſing the reſt very courteouſly; which made him confeſs he was truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, ſince, after ſo many Battles, his Enemy had overcome him in Kindneſs; and that it was ſome Comfort to him in his Miſery, to be ſubdued by ſo noble an Adverſary: However, another bloody Battle was fought on the Plains of <hi>Arbella,</hi> where the Perſians and Scithians at firſt prevailed, and with barbarous Shouts run on the Plunder; but ſuddenly an Eagle hovering over the Head of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> it was taken by his Men as a Preſage of Victory, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving their fainting Spirits, made them fall on ſo deſperately, that with the Battle they won him the Empire of the Eaſt; for <hi>Darius</hi> flying, was taken by <hi>Neorbarzanes</hi> and <hi>Beſſus,</hi> two of his own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, bound in Chains, and laid on a Waggon, thinking with the Head of their King to purchaſe their own Conditions with
<hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> but being hotly purſued, they mortally Wounded him, and left his Body on the Land, where he expired, and was magnificent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buried by <hi>Alexander,</hi> who took Poſſeſſion of the Perſian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> having gotten the Empire of <hi>Darius,</hi> warred on many Nations, and coming to the great Indian Sea, after he had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come King <hi>Porus,</hi> who made a ſtout Reſiſtance, he wept, becauſe, as he ſuppoſed, there were no more Countries to conquor; and in his return, Kings ſubmitted every-where to him, and <hi>Theleſtus,</hi> Queen of the Amazons, came with 5000 Virgins arm'd, to requeſt him to lye with her, that ſhe might have a Son by ſo Great a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour; and had her Wiſh.</p>
               <p>Peace being now pretty well ſettled, <hi>Alexander</hi> laying aſide the Macedonian Faſhion, followed the Perſian Mode, as well in Apparel as in Riot and Luxury, making many drunken Banquets, in one of which he killed <hi>Clytus</hi> an aged General, who had done him great
<pb facs="tcp:54609:5"/> Service in his Wars; but being ſober, he exceedingly mourned his Death, refuſing Food for four Days; but afterward putting many of his Lieutenants to Death upon little Pretences, and growing Outragious in his Actions, <hi>Antipater,</hi> Lieutenant of <hi>Macedon,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Life, cauſed his Son <hi>Caſſander,</hi> who waited on the King, to Poiſon him at one of his Banquets; and ſo dying without an Heir, his mighty Empire was divided amongſt his great Captains, and his Body carried to <hi>Egypt</hi> and there buried.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The Life and glorious Actions of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> the first Emperour of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lius Caeſar,</hi> the great Roman Captain, and Emperour of the World, deſcended of the <hi>Julian</hi> Family, ſo called from <hi>Julius Aſcunius,</hi> the Son of <hi>Aeneas</hi> of <hi>Troy,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> from his being cut from his Mother's Womb, began very early to climb to the higheſt Honours, being made Prieſt of <hi>Jupiter</hi> at ſixteen Years of Age; and though he was grievouſly perſecuted by <hi>Syla,</hi> who, foreſeeing his riſing to Greatneſs, labour'd to deſtroy him; often ſaying, There were many Mariuſes in that Boy, he eſcaped his Hands, and ſtudied at <hi>Rhodes</hi> under <hi>A. Molon,</hi> the famous Orator, where he grew ſo perfect, that on all Occaſions he had moving Words at Command, which mightily favoured his Purpoſe, and once appeas'd a Mutiny in his Army, when the Soldiers in their Rage and Fury ſought his Life, And having paſſed the Offices of Queſtor in
<hi>Spain,</hi> and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People, he gained by his fair Speeches and Liberality ſo much Love amongſt the Vulgar, that they every-where extolled him to the Skies; eſpecially when he had ſucceſsfully fought againſt, and overthrown the Lieutenants of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> King of <hi>Pontus,</hi> and turned many to their Alliance, who were wavering and ready to Revolt: And, to ſtrengthen his Alliance, he married <hi>Cornelia,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Cinna,</hi> who had been four times Conſul; by whom he had a Daughter named <hi>Julia,</hi> after married to
<hi>Pompey</hi> the Great; when coming to the Temple of <hi>Hercules,</hi> and ſeeing the Statute of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, he wept, becauſe he had lived to his Age, and had done nothing to compare with him: And ever after it put ſuch an Aſpiring into his Mind, that he grew reſtleſs till he ſubdued to himſelf the Roman Empire, far larger in Extent than that that
<hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> had poſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>After he had done many obliging things, to bind the Affection of the People of <hi>Rome</hi> to his intereſt, he was made Conſul with <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> and ſoon ſo prevailed over his Partner, that he laid him aſide,
<pb facs="tcp:54609:5"/> and acted alone in all Publick-Affairs; managing the Farms and Revenues of the Roman People to great Advantage; cauſing <hi>Cato</hi> to be violently pulled out of the Senate houſe, and committed, for interrupting him: for which he incurred his mortal Hatred ever after. And his Wife dying, he married <hi>Calphurnia,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Piſo;</hi> which ſo ſtrengthen'd his Alliance, that he awed the Senate.</p>
               <p>Soon after he went with the Conſullary Army over the <hi>Alps,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
<hi>France,</hi> then <hi>Gallia,</hi> and a great part of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſailing over into <hi>Britain,</hi> after many dangerous Battles fought with the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, he ſubdued a great Part of this Iſland, in his three Expeditions, and laid a Tribute of 3000 Pound Weight of Silver on the Natives, to be paid Yearly to the Romans. And when he had warred ten Years ſucceſsfully abroad, hearing that <hi>Pompey</hi> had made a great Party againſt him in the Senate, and that they were about to diveſt him of all his Honours, and calling him home as a private Man, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing <hi>Domitius</hi> his Succeſſor in <hi>Gallia,</hi> he was much diſturbed, and ſetling his Affairs as well as he could reſolved to march with his Army to <hi>Rome,</hi> though upon a Table of Braſs, placed on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the River <hi>Rubicon,</hi> whereon was engraven an Act of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, that no Roman ſhould paſs that River homeward Armed; when encamping on the Bank of that River, he pauſed a while, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to thoſe about him, <hi>Thus far we are ſafe, and may return if we pleaſe; If we paſs this Bridge, we ſhall have nothing to trust to, but our Arms.</hi> When he had ſpoke theſe Words, there appeared a Perſon of remarkable Stature and Beauty, playing melodiouſly on a Reed, which made many flock about him, when ſnatching a Trumpet out of one of their Hands, he ſtalked through the River, ſounding a Charge; whereat <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſeemed to be much amazed, though it was thought to be a Device of his to draw on his Men more willingly, and crying out, <hi>Come then, it is decreed;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> go where the Progenies of the Gods, and the Iniquities of our Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and immediately cauſing his Eagles to advance, he paſſed the forbiddes River; at the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of whoſe Approach, <hi>Petreus Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nas,</hi> young
<hi>Syla,</hi> and moſt of <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Lieutenants in <hi>Italy,</hi> deſerted the Towns, and fled; and the Maſſilians, and ſome others that made Reſiſtance, were reduced, into which Towns <hi>Caeſar</hi> putting Garriſons, marched to <hi>Rome,</hi> for Fear of whom,
<hi>Pompey</hi> and the Senate fled with the greater Part of the Inhabitants, whereupon he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> without Reſiſtance, and was received by his Friends with joyful Acclamations; then he ſeiz'd on the vaſt Treaſure, ſent by all Nations as Tribute, in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Saturn,</hi> enriching his Soldiers; and having ſettled Affairs, and hearing <hi>Pompey</hi> was gathering forces in <hi>Greece,</hi> and other Eaſter
<pb facs="tcp:54609:6"/> Countries, he haſted after him with Part of his Army; leaving <hi>Mark Anthony</hi> with the reſt in <hi>Calabria,</hi> who lingering behind, <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> impatient of Delay, in a ſtormy Night ſtole from his Army, and in a little Fiſher-boat paſſed the Seas to fetch them; a Danger the meaneſt of his Soldiers would not have ventured: And then, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his full Army, after ſome Skirmiſhes and taking of Towns, and drawing a Bullwark about
<hi>Pompey</hi>'s Army of fifteen Miles in Circuit, both Armies upon the Plains of
<hi>Theſſaly,</hi> joyned in a dreadful Battle, where <hi>Craſtinus,</hi> an old Soldier, crying out, <hi>O</hi> Caeſar, <hi>I ſhall ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my ſelf this Day, praiſe me alive or dead;</hi> threw the firſt Pile, and was himſelf ſlain, being run through the Mouth with a Sword. In this Battle, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as in all others, was victorious, moſt of the Senators and noble Romans, with 40000 others, being ſlain, and <hi>Pompey</hi> fled to <hi>Egypt</hi> for Succour from King <hi>Ptolomy;</hi> and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited on Shore with great Promiſes of Kindneſs, was treacherouſly ſlain e're he landed, by <hi>Achilles</hi> and <hi>Septinus,</hi> and his Head cut off, and that Embalmed for <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s fight; but he coming into
<hi>Egypt,</hi> not only deteſted the baſe Murther, but wept over the Head, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, with the Body, honourably to be buried. But ſoon <hi>Phati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and others of the Court conſpired to take his Head, but by his Courage and Fortune were prevented, by his firing the Ship-houſe, and ſwimming to his own Fleet, after which, he conquered all <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> and the King in his Flight being drown'd in the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> he made <hi>Cleopatra</hi> his Siſter, Queen, and begot on her a Son named <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> afterwards ſlain by the Command of <hi>Octavius Auguſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſettled Affairs in <hi>Egypt,</hi> he overthrew <hi>Pharnaces,</hi> who had rebelled in
<hi>Aſia,</hi> and in the Field of <hi>Thapſus</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> in a bloody Battle overthrew <hi>Cipio,</hi> the Roman General, and <hi>Juba</hi> King of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> who joyned his Forces with him. Then coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> had all the Honours he could wiſh heaped on him: But <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi>'s Son raiſing a War in <hi>Spain,</hi> drew him thither, where, in the fatal Battle of <hi>Munday,</hi> he overthrew them. Then returning to <hi>Rome,</hi> was decreed by the Senate Perpetual Dictator, ever <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and Father of his Country, had Temples and Statues erected to his Honour, and, without Controul, whatever he pleaſed. But at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to be made a King that he might overcome the Parthians, <hi>Brutus</hi> and
<hi>Caſſius,</hi> with other Senators, conſpired againſt him; and though ſeveral unlucky Dreams and Omens fore-run his Death, as his Dreaming he was taken up into the Clouds, and ſhook Hands with <hi>Jupiter;</hi> his Wife's dreaming the Night before he was ſlain, ſhe found him ſtabbed, and bloody in her Arms; a little Wren flying with a Laurel-branch to <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Theatre, was pulled to pieces by
<pb facs="tcp:54609:6"/> other Birds; and all the Sacrifices appearing unlucky, yet undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he went to the Senate-houſe, and pocketed by the way a Scrole preſented him unread, that revealed the whole Conſpiracy; but no ſooner had he taken his Seat, but <hi>Cimber</hi> rudely took him by the Shoulders, and the reſt ſtabbed him with twenty three Wounds, he in vain reſiſting ſuch a Multitude: And thus this Worthy, never overcome, but always fortunate in Wars, fell a Sacrifice to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Gown-men; but his Death was ſeverely revenged on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> The famous Life and Renowned Acts, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Captain General of the Iſraelites, who ſubdued thirty Kings, with the whole Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the mighty Hand of God, with many Signs and Wonders, had brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of their Egyptian Bondage, fed and inſtructed them forty Years in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, he having Notice to prepare for his Death by the Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, choſe
<hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun,</hi> to ſucceed him as Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain General of the People, and utterly to ſubdue the Canaanites on the other ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> as he had done on this ſide. When going up into Mount <hi>Abarim Moſes</hi> died, and was buried by God in a Valley, leaſt the Iſraelites, who had a great Veneration for him, knowing the Place of his Burial, ſhould have builded an Alter there, and committed Idolatry in Worſhipping him.</p>
               <p>Upon Notice that <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, <hi>Joſhua</hi> encamped two Days before the River
<hi>Jordan,</hi> and on the third the Prieſts entered with the Ark of God, when immediately the Waters retreated, and ſtood like a Wall on either Hand, ſo that the whole Army, whilſt the Prieſts ſtood in the middle, paſſed over on dry Ground; and then they took twelve Stones, according to the Tribes, and raiſed as a Monument to ſucceeding Ages: And no ſooner were the Prieſts come out of the River, but the Waters returned to their full Forces before. And the Princes of the Tribe of <hi>Gad,</hi> and <hi>Rhuben,</hi> and the Half Tribe of
<hi>Manaſſes,</hi> to whom the Land of the Amorites, being the ſeventh Part of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> fell as a Lot of Inheritance, having ſent 50000 fighting Men to aſſiſt their Brethren in conquering the reſt: <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſent Spies to <hi>Jerico,</hi> to view that ſtrong fenced City, who had been deſtroyed upon Notice of their coming, had not
<hi>Rahab,</hi> the Harlot, hid them under Bundles of Linnen till the Search was over, and then let them down by the Wall in a Basket, ſo they eſcaped to <hi>Joſhua;</hi> by which good Office ſhe ſaved herſelf and her Houſhold, when the City was utterly deſtroyed, for
<hi>Joſhua</hi> immediately went againſt it; and by the command of God, the Prieſts encompaſſed
<pb facs="tcp:54609:7"/> it ſix Days, blowing Trumpets of Rams-horns, and on the ſeventh Day ſeven times, when by the mighty Power of God, the Walls fell flat to the Ground, and the whole Army marching into the City deſtroy'd all the People, <hi>Rahab</hi> and her Houſhold accepted, and burnt it with Fire; laying up the rich Spoil as the Firſt-fruits of their Victory, as a Dedication to God Almighty, except a Wedge of Gold, and a rich Babilonian's Garment; which <hi>Achan</hi> with-held, and hid in his Tent; but going againſt <hi>Aii,</hi> a ſtrong fenced City, and the Men of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> being there diſcomfitted, and thirty of them ſlain, this Fraud was diſcovered to be the Cauſe of it, and <hi>Achan</hi> ſtoned to Death; after which, they took
<hi>Aii,</hi> and put all to the Sword, except the King, who, taken alive, was hanged on a Tree; as the like alſo they did by the City of <hi>Bethel,</hi> and the rich Spoil was divided amongſt the People.</p>
               <p>The Gibeonites, who dwelt in a Town near <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> hearing how <hi>Joſhua</hi> deſtroyed all before him, dealt craftily, ſending Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, pretendedly from a far Country, wearing old Shooes and Cloaths, with rent Bottles and mouldy Bread, to make a League; which they did, but for this Deceit, they were neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs puniſhed, by being made Slaves to hew Wood and draw Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Camp. And when the King of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and other Confederate Kings aſſembled a mighty Army utterly to deſtroy them, for making this League with the Enemies of their Country, upon their Supplication, <hi>Joſhua</hi> made a hard March to their Relief, and utterly, in a terrible Battle, diſcomfited the Kings and their Armies; and to lengthen out the Day for their Diſtruction, at the Prayer of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the Son and Moon, that were haſtening to ſet, ſtood ſtill for the ſpace of a whole Day, ſo that there was no Day like that Day in which God fought for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by deſtroying Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of their Enemies with mighty: Hail ſtones that fell upon them, yet hurt not one of the purſuing Iſraelites; and their five Kings being found hid in the Cave <hi>Mukkeda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Joſhua</hi> pulled them out, and cauſed the People to ſet their Feet upon their Necks in Token of Subjection, ſlew them, and hanged them on five Trees; burning
2000 War-charriots with Fire; and then marched through all the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> taking Cities and Strong holds, and in five Years utterly ſubdued it, unleſs ſome few ſtrong Garriſons; and having cauſed is to be viewed divided it amongſt the Tribes by Lot of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had appointed, ſetting up the Tabernacle of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shiloe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This famous War as it was thus finiſhed, the fifty Thouſand, whoſe Lot was in the Land of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> returned with great
<pb facs="tcp:54609:7"/> Riches to their Wives and Children; and that the parting of the River <hi>Jordan</hi> might not in time to come make them be taken for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother People, they erected an Altar there, which by a Miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding had like to have created a bloody War between their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren and them; but the real Cauſe being known, it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Joſhua</hi> having Governed ſucceſsfully twenty Years, and grown Old, finding the time of his Death approaching, aſſembled the Princes and Heads of the ePple, and gave them a ſtrict Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Obey the Lord their God in all things; that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Mouth of his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to walk uprightly in his ſight, that it might be well with them and their Children for ever. And ſoon after he died, greatly lamented of the People, in the
110th Year of his Age, and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e World's Creation 2560. and before the coming of Chriſt 1500.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The Life and glorious Reign of <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DAvid</hi> the renowned King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Captain of the Peple of the Lord of Hoſt, was the Son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> who, in his young Years, kept his Father's Flocks, and was then very Daring and Valiant, as appears by his fighting with, and killing a Lion and a Bear, who came to devour his Sheep: and when <hi>Saul,</hi> King of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinned againſt God in diſobeying his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, this Striplin was appointed to Reign over <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and by a ſpecial Command was annointed King by <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet: And the firſt of his publick Appearance, to make himſelf known, and to riſe to Greatneſs, was when <hi>Saul</hi> and his Armies were defied by <hi>Goliah,</hi> the great Giant of <hi>Gath,</hi> whom he ſlew with a Sling and a Stone; and had <hi>Michol</hi> the King's Daughter in Marriage, as it had been promiſed to him that ſhould overcome that daring Champion of the Philiſtines, who had been a Man of War from his Youth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and highly was he favoured in the Court of <hi>Saul,</hi> by <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> the Captain of the Hoſt, with the Giant's Head in his Hand: But after his many Victories, the Virgins in their Songs aſcribed to him ten Thouſands of Slain, and to <hi>Saul</hi> but one, which ſtirred up his Jealouſie and Envy againſt him, without his deſerving it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> no ſooner became renowned at Court, and throughout all the Land of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> but <hi>Jonathan, Saul</hi>'s eldeſt Son, and a very vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, made a very ſtrict League of Friendſhip with him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they became as own Brothers, he labouring to pacifie his Father's Wrath towards <hi>David,</hi> till he incurred it himſelf, and
<pb facs="tcp:54609:8"/> narrowly eſcaped Death, as <hi>David</hi> had often done; <hi>Saul</hi> by this time having Notice that by God's Appointment <hi>David</hi> was to be King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his Spirit was ſo troubled, that at times he fell into a melancholy Madneſs, ſo that an evil Spirit poſſeſſed him; and when <hi>David</hi> was playing before him on his Harp, as he often did to drive away the Spirit, <hi>Saul</hi> falling into one of his Fits, narrowly miſt ſlaying him, by throwing a Javelin at him with ſuch Force that it ſtuck in the Wall, and
<hi>David</hi> fled for his Life; and <hi>Saul</hi> ſent Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to purſue him, and beſet his Houſe, where he had been taken, but that his Wife let him down a Back-way, and laid an Image in his Bed, pretending he was ſick, till he eſcaped to the City of <hi>Nob,</hi> where of
<hi>Abimelech</hi> the High-Prieſt he obtained Shew-bread for his Suſtenance, and the Sword of
<hi>Goliah,</hi> kept there as a Monument, for his Defence; of which <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite informing, all the People belonging to that place were ſlain by <hi>Saul</hi>'s Command, as Abettors to his Enemy; which News greatly grieved <hi>David,</hi> who then made his aboad in the Woods and Mountains: And many were the Perſecutions he endured from that time, till <hi>Saul</hi> and his Sons being diſcomfitted by the Philiſtines, fell on their Swords, and died on Mount
<hi>Gilboa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Death of <hi>Saul, Abner</hi> his Uncle, after ſome Battles fought againſt
<hi>David,</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Iſhoſheth, Saul</hi>'s Son, upon a Quarrel between them about <hi>Riſpha,</hi> one of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Concubines, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Maſter, and made an Agreement with <hi>David,</hi> to ſettle him in the Kingdom: which he performed, by drawing the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to his Party; and <hi>David</hi> was ſaluted King: but <hi>Joab</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>David</hi>'s Hoſt, envying a Man that had ſuch great Power with the People, and become a new Favourite with the King, to his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, ſecretly ſent for him to treat about Affairs at <hi>Hebron,</hi> and there in the Gate treacherouſly killed him; whoſe Death
<hi>David</hi> greatly lamented; but <hi>Joab</hi> being powerful in the Army, he durſt not puniſh him for it. And ſoon after <hi>Iſhoſheth,</hi> the late King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was murthered, whoſe Murtherers <hi>David</hi> cauſed to be put to a cruel Death. And ſoon after the Philiſtines invading the Land, he overthrew them in two great Battles, and extended his Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by Victories over the Moabites and Ammonites, and Weſtward upon the Phoenetians, warring with the Arabians, Syrians, Hume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Amalekites, and Meſſopotamians, and much enlarged his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to which it was in the time of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> or ever before his Reign; and ſettling his Affairs in Peace and Plenty, the great Decayers of Virtue, he unhappily caſt his Eyes from his Tarras on the beautiful naked Body of <hi>Berſheba,</hi> Wife to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> one of his faithful Captains,
<pb facs="tcp:54609:8"/> as ſhe was Bathing in a Fountain, ſent for her, and lay with her; and when ſhe had told him ſhe was with Child, he ſent for her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to cover the Shame; but he refuſing to lie with her, he ſent Letters by him to <hi>Joab</hi> to have him deſtroy'd; who, as he was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, ſet him in the Front of the Battle, and retired from him, ſo that he ſell by the Sword of the Ammonites: And <hi>David</hi> took <hi>Barſheba</hi> to be his Wife: and after the Prophet had reproved him, he wept bitterly; but that Child dying, he begot on her
<hi>Solomon,</hi> who after was King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Yet God puniſhed him for this Sin, by the Raviſhment of his Daughter <hi>Tamar,</hi> the Murther of his Son <hi>Amnon;</hi> and laſtly, by the Rebellion of his Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who drove him almoſt out of his Kingdom; and was, contrary to the King's Command, after a great Defeat, ſlain by <hi>Joab</hi> as he hung by the Hair of the Head in an Oak; whoſe Death <hi>David</hi> lamented in a very ſorrowful manner, till <hi>Joab</hi> rebuked him; and compelled him to ſpeak comfortably to the People, whoſe Sorrow had utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartened them.</p>
               <p>After this Victory won, <hi>David</hi> was carried back with the Conſent of all the People to
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where having pardoned <hi>Shimei,</hi> that curſed him in his Flight, angry with <hi>Joab,</hi> he made <hi>Amaſa</hi> Captain of his Hoſt, who had headed
<hi>Abſolom</hi>'s Army; but <hi>Joab</hi> ſlew him in the way as they were marching in purſuit of <hi>Sheba,</hi> a Captain who had rebelled, whom he beſiged in <hi>Adelda,</hi> where his Head, by the Perſwaſion of a Woman of that City, was cut off, and thrown over the Wall; upon which <hi>Joab</hi> raiſed the Siege. Yet <hi>David</hi> having numbred the People, againſt the Advice of his Councellors, to know what Strength he had, God was diſpleaſed, and ſent a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that conſumed a great number of them.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>David</hi> having reigned eleven Years in Peace, betook himſelf to Piety and Devotion, writing his Hymns and Pſalms in the Praiſe of God, and preparing Materials to build the Temple, and when he had reigned forty Years he died in the ſeventy ſecond Year of his Age, appointing his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> to ſucceed him in the Throne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> The Life and valiant Actions of <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> Captain of the Iſraelites, against <hi>Atiochus</hi> the Perſecuting King of <hi>Syria.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMong other famous Worthies of the World, who ſtood as a Bulwark in the Defence of their Country, and by true Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, with ſmall Numbers, got almoſt incredible Victories over the Multitude of their Enemies, I muſt worthily rank <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> the renowed Captain of the Jews.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54609:9"/>In the youthful Days of this valiant Heroe, ſome of the looſer ſort of the Jews being puniſhed for their Diſorders, and the Neglect of their Religion, fled to <hi>Antiochus Epiphanius,</hi> who reigned over <hi>Syria,</hi> and a great part of <hi>Aſia,</hi> being one of thoſe Greek Captains who had parted <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Empire amongſt them: This cruel King, they earneſtly ſolicited to invade <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who in the Year of the World 3796, ſent a great Army to invade the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> who ſlaughtered all that fell in their way, burning and deſtroying their Towns and Strong-holds, and had <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> betrayed to him by the Factious Party; who, over-powering the others, open'd the Gates and let in the Army, where they ſacrilegiouſly robbed the Temple, carrying away the Golden Table, Candleſticks, and Cenſures, with all other Veſſels and Things of Value, dedicated to the Worſhip of God; raiſing a cruel Perſecution againſt the believing Jews, who refuſed to fall down and Worſhip their Idols, fleying ſome alive, roaſting and broiling others, boiling ſome in Cauldrous, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeven Sons of the <hi>Maccabes</hi> to horrible Torments, by broil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them on Grid-irons, and frying them in Braſs Pans alive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Torments they overcame with a admirable Patience, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Courage, till Death eaſed them, and gave laſting Joys for ſhort Pain. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> threw the Altars, ſlew the Prieſts, and ſtrangled their Children in the Arms of their weeping Mothers, and prophanded the Temple of God with abominable Sacrifices.</p>
               <p>In the time of this Diſſolation in the Holy City, and others, God ſtired up the Spirit of
<hi>Matthias,</hi> Father of <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Deliverance of his People from the Cruelties of the Heathen Tyrant. This Man was a Prieſt, who with his valiant Sons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Godly Jews, retired to the City of <hi>Modin,</hi> where he was ſoon ſummoned to ſurrender, and ſubmit himſelf, and all with him, to the Tyrant's Mercy; but he refuſed, and calling the People together, repeated all the miſeries and Cruelties the Nation of the Jews had ſuffer'd; exhorted them to be couragious, and truſt in God, as he and their Fathers had done in the like Diſtreſs, and revenge them on their Mercileſs Enemies: with other encouraging Words, which made them take Heart and reſolve to ſtand in Defence of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Lives, and fight on the Sabbath-day if they were aſſaulted, which before they had refuſed for fear of breaking it, ſuffering their Throats to be cut without Reſiſtance, their Enemies hunting 'em out in Woods and Caves whether they were fled, and chuſing for that Purpoſe, to fall on them on that Day: And whilſt they were thus conſulting, an irreligious Jew, to pleaſe the King's Commiſſioners, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tly ſtept forth and ſlewis Swine on the Altar, to do Sacrifice
<pb facs="tcp:54609:9"/> to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> when <hi>Matthias</hi> in his Zeal ſlew the Jew, and overthrew the Altar, and ſlaying <hi>Appolonius</hi> the King's Captain, and other Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that reſiſted; he cryed out, <hi>All you that are affected to the Law of your Fathers, and to the Service of God, follow me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, he aſſembled a great Company, overthrew his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Armies, and ſlaughter ed Multitudes of them; putting to Death many of the Apoſtate Jews; but being very aged, he recommended to them as their Captain, his Son, <hi>Judas Macchabeus,</hi> and when he had exhorted them to be Couragious, and expect the Divine Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, he gave up the Ghoſt.
<hi>Judas</hi> after his Father's Death, took on him the full Command, and overthrew
<hi>Antiochus</hi> his Lieutenant of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſlew him with moſt of his Army, taking great Spoil. After this, <hi>Seron</hi> Governour of <hi>Coeloſyria,</hi> came upon him with a great Army, when <hi>Judas</hi> encouraging his Men to truſt in God, who with a ſmall Force could confound the Mighty, and to fight like valiant Men, he fell like a Tempeſt on the General, and in a bloody Battle ſlew him and 800 Syrians, getting great Spoil of their Tents and Armour. Theſe unexpected Defeats ſo enraged <hi>Antiochus,</hi> that he commanded
<hi>Lyſias</hi> Governour of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to march with all the Power of that Country, and utterly deſtroy the Jews, or ſell them for Slaves to thoſe that would give moſt, and utterly to lay <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> waſt: Upon this, <hi>Lyſia</hi> raiſed a huge Army, and ſent them under the leading of <hi>Ptolomy, Nicanor</hi> and <hi>Georgias,</hi> three prime Captains, and Men of great Authority with the People: whereupon <hi>Judas</hi> and his Men called on <hi>God</hi> for Aſſiſtance, proclaiming a Faſt, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves before him, and then fell upon their Enemies with great Fury, with only 3000 Men, ſo that he ſoon put them to the Rout, covering the Field with dead Bodies, and ſlew them in the Purſuit to the Plains of
<hi>Idumea,</hi> and then returned to the Spoil; and ſoon after overthrew <hi>Lyſias,</hi> who invaded <hi>Judea</hi> with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of 60000 Foot and 5000 Horſe, with a mighty Slaughter, ſo that <hi>Lyſias</hi> returned to <hi>Antioch</hi> to recruit his broken Army; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<hi>Judas</hi> exhorted the People, that as an Acknowledgment of God's Favour and Goodneſs in giving them ſo many Victories, they ſhould go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> purge the Temple, and offer Sacrifice; which they did with much Devotion, giving Praiſe and Thanks to Almighty God for their Deliverance, rebuilding the Altars, and repairing the Breaches.</p>
               <p>After this, he ſet upon his Enemies, and waſted them round about <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> relieving thoſe Jews that were diſtreſſed by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by his Brother
<hi>Simeon,</hi> whom he ſent with an Army unto <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liles</hi> and other places; obtaining theſe and many other gallant Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:54609:10"/> with little Loſs of Men, which made <hi>Antiochus</hi> ſtorm, and in the End, ſend <hi>Bacchides</hi> the Great Marſhal of his Army, with a mighty Force, even all the Strength of <hi>Syria;</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> having but few in number, many being fled for Fear, nevertheleſs, contrary to the Mind of his Captains, who deſired him to retreat till he was better recruited, gave Battle, and the Jews fought like Lions, ſelling their Lives at a dear Rate; yet being over-powered by Numbers, and encloſed with the Multitude of their Enemies,
<hi>Judas,</hi> after he had ſlain many of the Enemies, weary with Killing, fainted, and fell to the Ground, where he was ſlain: But <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> recovered his Body, and buried it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> The Life and famous Actions of <hi>Arthur,</hi> King of the Britains, who ſubdued the Pagan Saxons, and drove them out of the Land, with many other great Exploits.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARthur</hi> of famous Renown and Memory, the Worthy King of the Britains, of whom ſo many wonderful Stories are related, as likewiſe of his valiant Knights of the Round Table, was, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to true Hiſtory, paſſing others over, the Son of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter Pendragon,</hi> got on the fair <hi>Igrene,</hi> Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Cornwal;</hi> and tho' he was born out of Wedlock, yet afterward <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter</hi> married his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and left him Heir to his Kingdom, tho' he had two Siſters, one married to the King of the Scots, and the other to the King of the Picts; which Kings, were highly diſpleaſed, that <hi>Arthur,</hi> who was not Legitimate, ſhould ſucceed to the Crown in bar of their pretended Right; and the Saxons, who a conſiderable time before had been called in by <hi>Vortegern,</hi> under the Leading of their two Captains,
<hi>Hihgest</hi> and <hi>Horſa,</hi> as Aid againſt the Picts and Scots, who miſerably harazed the Britains, when the Romans withdrew their Forces to ſupport their tottering Empire, having of Servants forcibly poſſeſſed themſelves of moſt of the Eaſt and Northern Parts of what is now called <hi>England, Loth,</hi> the Pictiſh King who had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the eldeſt Siſter, finding he could not by his Ambaſſadors pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the Britains to admit him their King, but that they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted <hi>Arthur,</hi> they diſdaining to ſubmit to a Stranger, when they had ſo Valiant and Worthy a Native to defend them, he joyned League with the Saxons, ſoliciting the King of Scots to do the like, reſolving utterly to exterpate the Britiſh Name from off the Face of the Earth.</p>
               <p>The Knowledge of this Confederacy ſoon rouzed King <hi>Arthur,</hi> when leaving the Pleaſures of his Court, and having raiſed an Army
<pb facs="tcp:54609:10"/> of his own Subjects, and received ſome Forces from <hi>Armorica,</hi> or <hi>Little Britain</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> he marched couragiouſly againſt the Eaſtern Saxons to give them Battle, e're the Picts ſhould joyn their Forces; and meeting their Army very numerous, about ten Miles from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> he vanquiſhed them in two bloody Battles, and made them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Tributaries, and receive over them ſuch Governours as he appointed, with many other hard Conditions. After this, he took <hi>London,</hi> and held a kind of a Parliament of the Britiſh Eſtates, wherein it was agreed to recruit the Army, and ſpeedily march Northward againſt thoſe beyond the River <hi>Humber;</hi> when in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> he fought the Picts and Saxons who had joyned their Armies, and overthrew them with a terrible Slaughter, purſuing the flying Saxons to <hi>York,</hi> where he beſiged them; but Scarcety and Sickneſs growing in his Army, and hearing great Multitudes of Picts and Saxons, who had paſſed the Seas from
<hi>Germany,</hi> under <hi>Occa</hi> their Captain, were coming to Relieve them, he broke up the Siege, and retired into <hi>Wales;</hi> but early in the Spring marched to <hi>London,</hi> and ſettling Affairs with the Saxons of <hi>Kent,</hi> marched Northward, and overthrew
<hi>Colgern</hi> and <hi>Occa,</hi> two Captains that were ravaging the Country, and took the City of <hi>York,</hi> ſparing the Lives of the Inhabitants, and concluded a League with <hi>Loth</hi> King of Picts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was concluded, that <hi>Mordred, Loth</hi>'s eldeſt Son, ſhould ſucceed <hi>Arthur,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Britain;</hi> and in the mean time with Joynt Forces help to expel the Saxons; and that <hi>Mordred</hi> ſhould marry the Daughter of
<hi>Gawolum,</hi> a noble Britain, and the Children to be brought up by the Grandfather in
<hi>Britain.</hi> And in this League was included the King of Scots, who at King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Deſire, joyned their Forces near <hi>Tinmouth,</hi> where they overthrew the Saxons with a terrible Slaughter, killing <hi>Colgern</hi> and <hi>Childrick,</hi> two of their chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captains, ſo that the remaining Saxons were ſo diſheartened, that moſt of them left the Kingdom, others ſubmitted to live peaceably under ſuch Governours as ſhould be appointed them, and turned Chriſtians, at leaſt in Shew; and ſuch as ſtayed after Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and refuſed to be Baptized, ſuffered Death. Then the King repaired ſeveral Churches the Pagan Saxons had ruinated. But the Saxons of the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> joyning with thoſe of
<hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> fell ſurprizingly upon the Britains that inhabited amongſt them, flew them, and made Spoil of their Goods; but the King, with the Aid of the Picts and Scots, marched againſt them, who feignedly ſent their Supplications to him, to treat about their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting the Land; but whilſt they were Treating, they fell upon the advanced Part of the King's Army, and killed many of them;
<pb facs="tcp:54609:11"/> and tho' their Commanders ſent to excuſe it, as done raſhly by ſome who were ignorant of the Treaty, the King reſolved to Puniſh ſuch Treachery, which he did by ſetting upon them with ſuch Fury, that few of their great Army eſcaped the Slaughter; and many, urg'd by the devouring Sword behind, threw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the River to avoid it, and were drowned, and ſo the Land was cleared of all, but thoſe who complied to the Terms beforementioned: And in this Battle, with his Sword called <hi>Callibourn,</hi> ſome Hiſtories ſay he ſlew 800, but this looks ſomething incredible; but certain it is, he returned Victorious from twelve ſet Battles, beſides Skirmiſhes, the 1ſt at the River <hi>Gleyn,</hi> 2, 3, 4 and 5 at the River
<hi>Douglaſs</hi> in <hi>Lenox,</hi> 6 at the River <hi>Baſſus,</hi> 7 in the Callido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Wood, 8 near the Caſtle of <hi>Guiven,</hi> 9 at <hi>Carleon,</hi> 10 near <hi>Richwood,</hi> 11 on a Hill called <hi>Agued Cathbergain,</hi> and 12th at <hi>Bath,</hi> or <hi>Bathen</hi> Hill.</p>
               <p>Some Authors mention he had ſeveral Battles with the Danes and Norwigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and drove thoſe Invaders out of the Land; and when <hi>Lucius Hiberius,</hi> the Roman Legate, came to demand Tribute for <hi>Britain,</hi> King <hi>Arthur</hi> ſtoutly anſwered, That from
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, Son of <hi>Hellen,</hi> a Britiſh Princeſs, he claimed a Succeſſion to the Roman Empire, and would e're long come with an Army to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſubdue it, and make it Tributary to <hi>Britain;</hi> which ſtout Anſwer, ſo daſhed the Legate, that he return'd much troubled; and ſome write, but upon what Certainty, I know not, that this King paſſed the Seas with a Fleet of 1000 Sail of Ships, and a mighty Army, ſubduing
<hi>France, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after the Saxons were expelled, <hi>Loth,</hi> King of the Picts, dyed; and the Britains, unwilling a Stranger ſhould Reign over them, in a manner, by their Importunity compelled King
<hi>Arthur</hi> to exclude <hi>Mordred,</hi> now King <hi>Pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> from the Succeſſion, and to Adopt <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Son of <hi>Cador</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> a valiant and virtuous young Man; which Diſappointment ſo vexed <hi>Mordred,</hi> that after many threatning Meſſages, finding no Redreſs, he raiſed the Power of his whole Kingdom; to which many Scots joyned themſelves, and ravaged the Northern Parts, ſlaying and burning all in his way: And tho' ſeveral Biſhops on either Part laboured for a Reconciliation, they could not prevail; ſo that to decide the Controverſie, a dreadful Battle was fought, near the River
<hi>Humber,</hi> and the Britains being entangled among the Bogs and Quagmires, a Place that had been ever fatal to them, tho' they fought like Lions, yet in the end both Kings, with moſt of their Nobles being ſlain, with 20000 Picts and Scots, and 30000 Britains, the Day fell to the Picts and Scots, by a crafty Device of a Scot, who getting among the Britains, cryed, in the Britiſh Tongue, <hi>Our King and his Nobles are ſlain, every Man ſhift for himſelf;</hi> which wrought ſuch a Fear in the Army, that it fell in Rout before there was any Cauſe for it; and this Loſs was ſo great, that neither Nation recovered it in many Years.</p>
               <p>The Body of King <hi>Arthur</hi> being found covered with the Heaps he had ſlain, was honourably buried in <hi>Glaſtenbury</hi> Church-yard, in <hi>Summerſetſhire;</hi> and after his Death, the Saxons came again, and drove the Britains into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, taking ſtrong Poſſeſſion of all the plain Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:54609:11"/>
               <head>The Life and Glorious Actions of <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> or <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, who reſtored the Roman Empire in the West.</head>
               <p>WHen the barbarous Nations, as Goths, Huns, Sarazens, Vandels, Lumbards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had torn the Roman Empire in pieces, and divided it among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, grievouſly Perſecuting all that profeſſed the Name of Chriſt, GOD, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cries and Groans, and ſeeing the abundant Tears of his afflicted Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, raiſed them up Deliverers: And firſt <hi>Charles Martell,</hi> a French Prince, who taking Courage to reſcue his oppreſſed Country, raiſed an Army of 60000 French and Germans, who gave Battle to <hi>Abderamen,</hi> a King of the Sarazens, who had over run <hi>Franco,</hi> with an Army of 400000 Men, and overthrew him, with the ſlaughter of 375000 of his Men, and found him overwhelmed with a Heap of the Slain, and tho' not wounded, his Men in their Flight from the purſuing French Men, preſſed him to Death; and ſoon after overthrew with great Slaughter another King of the Sarazens, who was coming to Aid the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer with an Army of 300000 Men, utterly driving the Sarazens out of <hi>France</hi> and
<hi>Germany;</hi> for which worthy Service, after his Death, his Son <hi>Pepin,</hi> a valiant Prince, was made King; and <hi>Childrick,</hi> a lazy vicious Prince, of the Race of
<hi>Pharamond,</hi> laid aſide. This Man did many great Actions, much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging his Kingdom; and dying, divided his vaſt Dominions between his two Sons, <hi>viz. Charles</hi> or
<hi>Charlemagne,</hi> and <hi>Caroloman,</hi> the firſt being crowned at <hi>Wormes,</hi> and the laſt at <hi>Soiſſons;</hi> but long they agreed not, for <hi>Charles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a mild Temper, and <hi>Caroloman</hi> of a turbulent Spirit, he laboured to ſupplant him; and to that end, after ſome Conteſts, he joyned with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Charles,</hi> went to
<hi>Rome</hi> under a Pretence of Devotion, labouring to make the Pope his Friend, and to League himſelf to <hi>Didier,</hi> a powerful King of the Lombards in <hi>Italy,</hi> which wrought much Trouble to <hi>Charles,</hi> from the Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard and Pope. But within three Years after his being crowned, <hi>Caroloman</hi> dyed; and then, after ſtrugling with ſome Rebels, the whole Inheritance fell to <hi>Charles,</hi> who warred with the Saxons, Bavarians, and other Nations, ſixteen Years, and overcame them, making them his Tributaries: And when <hi>Didier,</hi> the King of the Lombards, went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and hanged the Pope's two Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for ſiding with
<hi>Charles,</hi> and cauſed the Pope to be depoſed, <hi>Charles</hi> having over come the Sons of <hi>Caroloman,</hi> who raiſed Diſturbances in <hi>France,</hi> to put themſelves in Poſſeſſion of their Father's Eſtate, he raiſed an Army, and paſſing the
<hi>Alps,</hi> entered into <hi>Italy,</hi> and in two great Battles defeated the Lombards, beſieging them and their King in <hi>Pavia,</hi> which was ſoon ſurrendred to him, and
<hi>Didier</hi> their King was ſent Priſoner to <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and ſo ended the Lombard Kingdom in <hi>Italy,</hi> which had long flouriſhed, and been the Terror of all that Country: and for this great Service, Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> in a Councel held at
<hi>Rome,</hi> decreed, That <hi>Charles</hi> ſhould have a Right of Diſpoſing of all the Eccleſiaſtical Benefits that became Vacant, throughout Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> no ſooner returned into <hi>France,</hi> but <hi>Aldegiſe,</hi> Son to
<hi>Didier,</hi> raiſed, Commotions in <hi>Italy,</hi> by the Helpe of <hi>Rogand,</hi> to whom
<hi>Charles</hi> had given the Country of <hi>Friuli;</hi> but by the Care and Vigilence of the French Governours, <hi>Rogan</hi> was taken, and by the King's Command loſt his Head, which ended the Sedition: And being now at Leaſure, he reſolved to War on the Sarazens
<pb facs="tcp:54609:12"/> and Moors, who coming over to <hi>Africa,</hi> had ſtrongly poſſeſſed themſelves of all <hi>Spain,</hi> and overthrew them in ſeveral Battles, taking the Cities of
<hi>Pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona</hi> and <hi>Saragoſa,</hi> and many other ſtrong Places, putting thoſe he found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the Sword for their Cruelty towards the Chriſtians; but <hi>Agoland,</hi> a Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen King, taking the Advantage of ſtreight Paſſages in the Mountains, fell upon
<hi>Milon,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Charles,</hi> and ſlew him, with moſt Part of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and elevated with this Victory, he marched into <hi>France,</hi> and beſieged <hi>Agen</hi> in
<hi>Gaſcoine,</hi> but <hi>Charles</hi> ſoon overtook him; yet his Troops with long Marches were ſo weary, that they were not at that time in a Condition to fight; yet <hi>Agoland</hi> propos'd a Way to decide the Difference, <hi>viz.</hi> That a Troop on either Party ſhould fight it out; and the Sarazen promiſed to turn Chriſtian, if his was beaten; and his Troop being worſted, and moſtly ſlain, he did become a Chriſtian in Shew, but ſeeing the King at Dinner, and a Table in the ſame Room at which many poor Men fed of the King's Bounty, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what they were; to which <hi>Charles</hi> anſwered, They were God's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters;
<hi>Nay,</hi> then ſaid the impious Sarazen, <hi>your God must needs be very poor himſelf, ſeeing his Miniſters are ſo very poor and contemtible;</hi> and ſo departed. But
<hi>Charles,</hi> to be revenged of him, followed him into <hi>Spain,</hi> overthrew him in a great Battle, and brought away his Head as a Trophy of his Victory.</p>
               <p>Thus this great Man having extended his Dominions very largely, was by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> whom he had delivered from his Enemies, crowned Emperour of the Weſt; and having ſettled his Empire over many Nations in Peace, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf to a quiet Life; he cauſed <hi>Lewis</hi> his Son to be crowned Emperour of the Romans, giving him good Exhortations to govern well that great Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed to his Charge, with a Regard to the Chriſtian Religion, Piety, and Mercy, having got him by his Sword and Prudence the Dominion over all <hi>France, Germany, Italy, Hungary, Poland,</hi> and Part of <hi>Spain;</hi> and ſo in the midſt of his Devotions he died in the 71 Year of his Age, when he had reigned 47 Years, and was a while layed in State, and then buried in a ſtately Monument in the Church of <hi>Aix,</hi> In a Chappel himſelf had founded, a little before for that Purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The Life and Glorious Actions of <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloign,</hi> Duke of
<hi>Lorain,</hi> who conquered the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and was crowned King of
<hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce many People have heard of a <hi>Holy War,</hi> and yet but few can tell to what Purpoſe it was made, or in what Region, I ſhall here, for their better Inſtruction, ſet forth a ſatisfactory Relation of it, in the Life and noble Actions of one of the famous Worthies of the World, <hi>Godfrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Bulloign, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> and <hi>Verdon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſo happened, for the Lukewarmneſs of the Eaſtern Chriſtians, and their furious Conteſts about Niceties in Religion, which cauſed a general Decay of Piety amongſt them, that God ſuffered them at firſt to be over-run, and their Countries taken from them by the barbarous Sarazens, and they being ſubdued by the Turks, all manner of Cruelties were uſed towards the Chriſtians, that ſtill inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited amongſt them in great Numbers, which made them groan under their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Bondage, and cry to God for Succour in their Diſtreſs; when the Patriarch of
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and other good Men aſſembling, it was reſolved to ſend one
<hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54609:12"/> a French Man, who had taken upon him the Life of a Hermit, with their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to the Weſtern Chriſtians, beſeeching them in the Bowels of Mercy and Compaſſion, to look with Eyes of Pity on their Sufferings, and with an armed Power reſcue them and the Holy City of
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> out of the Hands of the mercileſs Enemies of the Name Chriſt; this Man, after a tedious Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and eſcaping many Dangers, came to <hi>Rome, Anno</hi> 1093,
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond being then Biſhop of that See, to whom he delivered the Patriarch's Letters, and gave a full Account of the Matter ſo moving, that the Biſhop could not refrain from Tears, and ſummoning a Councel at <hi>Placentia,</hi> whither moſt of the Chriſtian Princes and Prelates were invited, where, appearing in full Aſſembly, the Pope with moving Orations, cauſing the Patriarch's Letters to be read, and <hi>Peter</hi> to declare the cruel Uſage the Eaſtern Nations ſuffered at the Hands of their Infidels, the Princes were ſo inflamed with a Zeal of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering their ſuffering Brethren, that with one Conſent they agreed to raiſe Forces immediately, and march to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> which unanimous Agreement, the Pope no ſooner perceived, but with Tears of Joy in his Eyes, he cried out, <hi>It is the Will of God;</hi> which Motto they put afterward in their Standard; and ſo the Counſel ending, every one repaired to their Country to raiſe Forces, which were to wear Red Croſſes on their Breaſts, to diſtinguiſh them; And the Chief of theſe were <hi>Godfrey</hi> of
<hi>Bulloign,</hi> and his two Brothers, <hi>Baldwin,</hi> and <hi>Euſtace; Hugh</hi> Earl of
<hi>Vermondois,</hi> the French King's Brother; <hi>Robert</hi> Duke <hi>Normandy,</hi> Son to our King <hi>William,</hi> Sir-named the Conqueror; <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Chartes</hi> and
<hi>Blois; Hugh</hi> Earl of St. <hi>Paul; Raymond</hi> Earl of <hi>Tholouſe; Robert</hi> Earl of
<hi>Flanders,</hi> with a great Number of Nobles, and Gentlemen, who lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an Army of 300000 valiant Men on the Shoars of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſtriking Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to their Enemies; and marching on, beſieged the City of <hi>Nice,</hi> the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal City of <hi>Bythinia,</hi> which
<hi>Solimon</hi> the Turkiſh Sultan of <hi>Perſia</hi> came with a a huge Army to relieve, but was utterly defeated, with ſuch Slaughter, that the Fields were covered with Blood, and the Bodies of the Slain. After which the Chriſtians returned again to their Siege, and Duke
<hi>Godfrey</hi> with an Arrow killed a mighty Giant-like Turk, who had manfully defended the Breach, tho' twenty Arrows were ſticking in his Breaſt, and killed the Aſſailants in great Numbers, with huge Stones which he threw at them; and ſoon after the City was taken, and delivered to <hi>Emanuel</hi> the Greek Emperor, in Lien of the Supplies of Proviſion he was to furniſh the Army withal.</p>
               <p>This City taken, they marched towards <hi>Syria</hi> in two Bodies, the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Chief by Duke <hi>Godfrey,</hi> and the other by the Duke of <hi>Normondy</hi> and the Earl of
<hi>Flanders,</hi> and in their Way being encountred by 300000 Turkiſh and Perſian Horſemen, they ſoon put them to the Rout, with incredible Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And having taken <hi>Tripolis,</hi> a ſtrong City in <hi>Syria,</hi> they advanced towards <hi>Antioch;</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> the Hermit, who had got together a great Multitude of Men out of the Territories of the Church, and from Monaſteries, whoſe Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was rather Eating than Fighting, advancing too far before the Army, and falling into an Ambuſh of the Enemy, moſt of them were ſlain, with their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: But the Army coming before the City of <hi>Piſidia,</hi> it ſurrendred. But new Duke
<hi>Godfrey</hi> going into the Woods to recreate himſelf, narrowly miſſed being ſlain by a monſterous Bear, whom he found aſſaulting one of his Soldier, who went to cut Wood; but though the Bear got him down, he drew his
<pb facs="tcp:54609:13"/> Sword under his Thigh, by which he wounded himſelf, and loſt much Blood, yet running it into the Belly of the Bear, he killed her: and on the like Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at another Time he, hearing a Lyon roar piteouſly in a Forreſt, and going to ſee what the Matter was, found a huge Serpent had twiſted itſelf about the Lyon's Legs, and with his poiſonous Sting was darting at his Head to kill him; but the Duke pitying the noble Lyon, with his huge Sword cut off the Sepent's Head, and relieved the Lyon; who in Gratitude, far ſurpaſſing moſt Men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after during his Life, followed him, hunted wild Beaſt for him, and fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on him like a Spannel, often defending him againſt his Enemies.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtians having conquered <hi>Siletia,</hi> and a great Part of <hi>Armenia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the City of <hi>Antioch,</hi> in which was a ſtrong Garriſon; and at their firſt ſetting down before it, Duke <hi>Godfrey,</hi> with a ſelected Party, only with their Swords in their Hands, defeated an Army of the Turks who ſay in Ambuſh to ſurprize his Soldiers ſent to fetch Proviſion for the Army at Port <hi>Simon,</hi> brought thither by Ships from
<hi>Genoa</hi> and <hi>Piſons,</hi> which the Pope had ſent for the Relief of the Chriſtians in <hi>Syria;</hi> and after a te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ge, took <hi>Antioch,</hi> and from thence marched towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>wing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Turks by the Way; when in one Battle, a Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k ſeeing Duke <hi>Godfrey</hi> beat down Multitudes before him, came on a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, all foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to encounter him with his mighty Cimiter, but after a fierce Encounter, the Duke with a forcible Stroak of his Sword, cut his Shoulder down to his Waſt, ſo that he fell dead from his Horſe.</p>
               <p>The Army coming within ſight of the Holy City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> fell on their Knees with devout Prayers for God's Aſſiſtance, vowing never to depart till they had taken it; and ſuch was their reſolute Courage, that they no ſooner came to the Walls, but immediately many ſcaled them, and beat the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants from the Battlements, leaping into the City, and tho' theſe were not ſeconded for want of Leaders, they ſold their Lives at a dear Rate. After this they lay'd a formal Siege, and it being extream hot Weather, they ſuffer'd much thro' Thirſt, for the Brook <hi>Kedron</hi> was dried up, and the Infidels had poiſoned all the Wells; yet that of <hi>Siloe</hi> had worked out the Poiſon, and the Water was become wholeſom, yet it yielded but little; however, they made many terrible Aſſaults, and at length enter'd by main Force, putting all the Turks and Sarazens to the Sword: And in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple found vaſt Riches; whilſt the Chriſtians there embraced the Soldiers with Tears, extolling them as their Deliverers.</p>
               <p>Now the City was taken, the Princes reſolved to ſettle a Chriſtian King therein, and the Lot fell upon the Duke of <hi>Normandy;</hi> but he minding his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teteſts nearer home, refuſed it: Then with a unanimous Conſent they choſe Duke <hi>Godfrey</hi> King, though he modeſtly refuſed ſo great an Honour; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it being preſſed upon him, he accepted it; but would not be crowned with a rich Crown that was offered him, ſaying, <hi>God forbid that any Chriſtian King ſhould wear a Crown of Gold, where his Saviour, for the Redemption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, had worn a Crown of Thorns.</hi> And the Princes having overthrown the Sultan of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who too late coming, to relieve the City; moſt of them took Leave of the King, and retutned home; who being buſied in enlarging his Frontiers, fell ſick, and dyed in the firſt Year of his Regin; and his Brother <hi>Baldwin</hi> ſucceeded him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
